בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ו vav and we
had just finished a fascinating discussion on שבת Shabbos on דף ה
daf hei about the minimum size of ten טפחים tefachim and just
to review that for one second because it's so important I think
in general and specifically of סוכה Sukkah ideas. So the question is
how do we know the minimum size of a סוכה Sukkah is
ten טפחים? tefachim? Twenty אמות amot we gave various reasons: ability to
see the סכך, skhach, the ability of the סכך skhach to give
shade, but the exact quantity exact number of twenty on twenty אמות
amot was determined by the Rabbis' application of that principle as opposed
to the idea of ten טפחים tefachim where the גמרא Gemara understands
that there's a more concrete derivation of exactly that number. And the
גמרא Gemara gave three reasons. The first one was we learn it
from the ארון, Aron, the ארון Aron was nine טפחים tefachim and
the כפורת Kaporet was one that makes ten. The second explanation was
the כרובים Keruvim on the ארון Aron that their wingspan over the
base of the ארון Aron was ten טפחים. tefachim. And the third
was which is going to be our focus today was just the
idea of הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai. It's just a straight
tradition. Now the first two, it's not exactly clear well the first
one particularly what that has to do with a סוכה. Sukkah.
And the גמרא Gemara basically says that well if the ארון Aron
and the כפורת Kaporet are ten טפחים tefachim and the divine presence,
the שכינה Shekhina hovered over the כפורת, Kaporet, so and the שכינה
Shekhina never went down to the earth, that's why the סוכה Sukkah
has to be ten טפחים. tefachim. Like seems completely bizarre what the
connection is. רש"י Rashi says that the connection is is that well
if ten טפחים tefachim close to the earth is the domain of
the earth, then a מחיצה mechitzah focusing on the walls of the
סוכה Sukkah has to be ten טפחים tefachim because it has to
go the entire height of the air space of a domain. And
according to that it's a general rule of מחיצה. mechitzah. However, as
we suggested at the time, a much more powerful idea is is
that it's the issue of סוכה Sukkah as the ענני הכבוד Ananei
HaKavod and God's divine presence hovering over the people not just the
clouds that sort of protected them but actually the cloud of God's
presence which is so present in the משכן Mishkan and so on
and that exact God's presence hovers over ten טפחים tefachim and it
hovers over the סוכה, Sukkah, then the סוכה Sukkah has to be
a minimum of ten טפחים, tefachim, it can't be lower because God's
presence can't come any lower. And then it becomes a very powerful
imagery of סוכות Sukkot with sort of you know as that sense
of reenacting the period in the desert and actually having a very
manifest and concrete experience of God's presence. And that's carried through by
the idea of the כרובים Keruvim although by the כרובים Keruvim it
understands that what we learn from the כרובים Keruvim is their wingspan,
it says it's סוככים sochechim shade the area below it canopies the
area below and that teaches us that the idea of סכך skhach
is ten טפחים tefachim because to create a sense of a canopying
of the space below. Nevertheless again what the גמרא Gemara is doing
is putting us in the discussion of סוכה Sukkah and in the
marvel of סוכה Sukkah right there in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim
and right there with that sort of immediate encounter with God. And
again thinking that this is coming on the heels of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur where יום כיפור Yom Kippur was all of this elaborate
ritual to allow the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to enter into the
קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and now comes סוכות Sukkot five days later
and we're envisioning the סוכה Sukkah as some reenactment or some sort
of experience of the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, of the ארון Aron
and the כפורת, Kaporet, the you know or of the כרובים Keruvim
and that sense of יום כיפור Yom Kippur leading to you know
and the forgiveness of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, מתן תורה Matan Torah
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur leading to that sense of you know
of the divine presence. So the imagery is very very powerful. And
then we get to the last answer which is the much more
sort of technical answer of no we just have a tradition that
ten טפחים. tefachim. But I don't but it's important to remember the
imagery there which is very powerful and seems to be really distinctive
to סוכה Sukkah although רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot try to make
it more general about the general idea of a מחיצה. mechitzah. So
now let's pick up from the גמרא. Gemara. And the גמרא Gemara
says like this: okay,
דאמר de'amar
about eight lines from the bottom דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר
רב de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav
שיעורין חציצין ומחיצין הלכה למשה מסיני. Shiurin Chatzitzin uMechitzin Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai.
שיעורין Shiurin minimum quantities, הלכות Halakhot
of חציצה Chatzitza
of obstructions when somebody goes to the מקוה mikvah and הלכות Halakhot
relating to מחיצה mechitzah one of which is the minimum height here
now the idea of ten טפחים tefachim is going to be a
מחיצה mechitzah issue not a סכך skhach issue, all of these
are הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai. שיעורין דאורייתא נינהו? Shiurin De'oraita
ninhu?
What do you mean it's like an oral tradition going back to
משה? Moshe? Actually it's דאורייתא. De'oraita. So quite fascinating דאורייתא De'oraita is
different than הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai. הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha
L'Moshe MiSinai is not linked in a verse, it's a tradition going
back to משה Moshe but it's not linked in a verse whereas
דאורייתא De'oraita means it's derived from a verse. Where do you see
it's דאורייתא? De'oraita? דכתיב, De'ktiv, the verse says: ארץ חטה ושעורה וגפן
ותאנה ורמון ארץ זית שמן ודבש. Eretz chittah u'se'orah gefen u'te'enah ve'rimon
eretz zeis shemen u'devash. So all of these things of the Land
of Israel. So, all of these things of the Land of Israel,
and now we're going to say: ואמר רבי חנין *Ve-amar Rabi Chanin*,
כל הפסוק הזה לשיעורין נאמר *kol ha-pasuk hazeh l'shi'urin ne'emar*. This entire
verse is telling you not just of all the foods that are
in Israel, all the amazing produce of the land, but that all
the, you know, from a תורה Torah *Torah* perspective it's like halachic
man, you know, you see a tree, you can't smell it or
feel it, all you could do is see its halachic category. So,
oh, that's ערלה *orlah*, שביעית *shvi'is*, or whatever. So, all of these
wonderful things are because all of the various produce of Israel gives
you the different basis for halachic שיעורין shiurin *shiurin*. How does this
work? נאמר *Ne'emar*... חטה *chita*, so wheat, for a בית המנוגע *beis
hamenuga* for a leprous house. דתנן *Detnan*, הנכנס לבית המנוגע *hanichnas l'veis
hamenuga*, somebody goes into a leprous house, וכליו על כתפיו *ve-keilav al
kseifav*, and your clothes are on your shoulder, you're not wearing them,
וסנדליו וטבעותיו בידיו *ve-sandalav ve-tab'otav beyadav*, and you're holding onto your sandal
and your rings, they're not on your... your ring isn't on your
finger, it's in the palm of your hand, הוא והן טמאין מיד
*hu ve-hein tmei'im miyad*, you and they are טמא tamei? *tamei* immediately.
דף ו vav, עמוד א *Daf vav amud aleph*. היה לבוש כליו
וסנדליו ברגליו *Haya lavush keilav ve-sandalav beraglav*, now let's say however it
wasn't that you were carrying these, you were wearing them, you were
wearing your clothes, your sandals were on your... were on your feet,
וטבעותיו באצבעותיו *ve-tab'otav be'etzba'otav*,
and your rings were actually being worn on your finger, הוא טמא
מיד *hu tamei miyad*, you are טמא *tamei* immediately, והן טהורין עד
שישהא כדי אכילת פרס *ve-hein tehorim ad she-yish'heh k'dei achilat pras*, and
you and they are טהור *tahor* until you wait the time it
takes to eat a half of loaf of bread. פת חטין ולא
פת שעורין *Pat chittin velo pat se'orin*, a loaf made out of
wheat flour, not barley flour. מיסב ואוכל בלפתן *Meisev ve-ochel
beliftan*, and eating in a focused way, so you're reclining and eating,
which for them would be the focused way of eating because that's
like your, you know, that's how you eat is when you recline
by the table and you put all your attention, and dipping it
into some sauce because, you know, when you dip it into a
sauce it goes faster. Okay, and that's
what... and that's what חטה *chita* tells us. What does this all
mean? It means that the תורה Torah *Torah* says that if somebody
comes into the house of a... that has leprosy, not of a...
of somebody who is a מצורע *metzora*, but the house itself has
the spot of leprosy, it says that... that you become טמא *tamei*.
Okay, but it says if you eat in the house, your clothes
become טמא *tamei*, you and your clothes become טמא *tamei*. And the
rabbis understand it doesn't literally mean eat, eat means you wait in
the house the time it takes you to eat. Okay, so that's
what it means. So if you just walk in, you're טמא *tamei*
immediately. If you're holding onto your clothes, then your clothes are just
seen as an object, as an... as any... you know, as any
generic object, and therefore they become טמא *tamei* immediately. But interestingly, if
you're wearing your clothes, that's when it says that if you eat
in the house, you and your clothes become טמא *tamei*, so it
means the clothes... so again, the rabbis interpret this meaning if you
wait in the house long enough to the time it takes to
eat, then the clothes that are being worn will become טמא *tamei*,
so it takes longer for the clothes that are being worn to
become טמא *tamei* than anything else, very bizarre. And it's the time
it takes to eat. Well, eat how much? So eat a meal.
What's a meal? A meal is a פרס *pras*, which is half
a loaf of bread, where a standard loaf of bread was two
meals' worth. What type of a loaf of bread? Well, it's wheat
bread. Wheat bread made, you know, reclining and dipping and all of
those criteria affect the amount of time it will take you to
eat it. So that's a שיעור *shiur* that's learned from the תורה
*Torah* that wheat determines the type of bread that we normally measure
when in ever הלכה halacha *halacha*, not only this by the way,
you know הלכה halacha *halacha*'s always saying that if you eat a
כזית kezayit, *kezayit* over the time of כדי אכילת פרס *k'dei achilat
pras*, it all combines to a minimum כזית kezayit. *kezayit*, like the
time it takes you to eat the כזית kezayit. *kezayit* of מצה
*matzah*, or if you're doing an עבירה *aveirah* and you're eating a
כזית kezayit, *kezayit* of נבילה *neveilah*, you know, the time it takes
to combine this אכילת פרס *achilat pras*, what type of half loaf
of bread? A half loaf of wheat bread. So that's where חטה
*chita* factors in to the הלכות halakhot *halachos* of שיעורין Shiurin... *shiurin*.
Yes.
So in this case, the house is an אבי הטומאה *avi hatumah*?
Yes. You're inside, you become a ראשון *rishon*. Right. And the clothes
don't become immediately a שני *sheni* because...
No, the clothes become a ראשון *rishon* too because they're inside.
But eventually they do, but if say... but clothes, you're touching the
clothes would ordinarily make them... No, clothes can't become a שני *sheni*.
Right. And that's why... that's the reason why there's that...
That is correct. That is correct. Okay. So, okay, so that's where...
we... that's where wheat is relevant for the laws of שיעורין Shiurin?
*shiurin*. So, שעורה se'orah *se'orah*, barley, דתנן *detnan*, we taught in a
משנה *mishna*, עצם כשעורה *etzem k'se'orah*, a piece of bone the size
of a... of a barley, of a... what would you call it,
a kernel of barley, what would you call it? A kernel of
barley. מטמא במגע ובמשא *metamei be-maga u-ve-massa*, so human bone, it's a
very even a tiny amount the size of a kernel of barley
causes טומאה tumah, *tumah* with touch and carrying, ואינו מטמא באוהל *ve-eino
metamei be-ohel*, but not in under a tent, you know, for a
corpse to cause טומאה *tumah* under a tent, under a rooftop, it
has to be something that's really representative of the whole corpse, and
a tiny bit of bone would not, it would need to be
the skull or most of the bones, other type... a much larger
amount. But nevertheless, you use a barley, a kernel of barley to
measure the minimum amount of bone to cause טומאה *tumah* by contact.
So that's שעורה *se'orah*. גפן *Gefen*, how about wine? כדי רביעית revyis
יין לנזיר *k'dei revi'it yayin l'nazir*, because a נזיר nazir *nazir* does
not transgress until he drinks a רביעית revyis *revi'it*, a quarter of
a לוג *log* of wine, about three and a half ounces. Now
there is a problem... with this, with this sort of application. What's
the problem? Until now חטה, שעורה are things you use to measure
other things.
How much what type of wheat? Wheat bread. How much bone? Barley's
worth of bone. Here we're saying: what does wine tell you? Oh,
you're only חייב chayav when you drink a רביעית revyis, of wine.
That's the thing being measured; it's not the basis of measurement, right?
And we already know in the תורה that a נזיר nazir can't
drink wine. So what's this telling us? רש"י Rashi has a brilliant
answer. I mean, there's a long תוספות, Tosafot, but I'll just give
you רש"י's Rashi answer. רש"י Rashi says, because a נזיר transgresses not
only when he drinks wine, but also when he drinks the solids
of the grapes, right? חרצנים וזג, chartzanim vezag, like grape, you know,
skins and the pits. So how much of that? So it's a
רביעית revyis actually, not a כזית, kezayit. at least according to one
approach. So if it's a רביעית, revyis so רש"י Rashi says: Well,
how do you measure a רביעית revyis of solids? How are you
going to measure a רביעית revyis. of, you know, grape leaves let's
say? So what's the way we do measurements of volume of things
that are
solids? Nowadays, what's the... right, water displacement, right? Liquid displacement. So רש"י
Rashi says, sure, you find you fill up something with, you know,
with liquid, you put in the thing and then a רביעית revyis
comes out and you know you have a רביעית. He says ah,
but what liquid do you fill it up with? Water or wine?
What difference does it make? Charlie, what difference does it make?
If you're measuring the volume, it doesn't make any difference at all.
Well, it does, because if you measure the weight, it doesn't...
the surface tension. Okay, so he says the surface tension of wine
is greater than the surface tension of water, so therefore in order
to measure a רביעית of wine displacement through the liquid displacement measure,
you're going to need a little bit more than if you were
doing a water because it'll take more to break the surface tension.
So that's how רש"י Rashi says is the
significance that you
use wine for the
in order to do the measurement using a water displacement or a
wine displacement. Okay, תוספות Tosafot has some other explanations. תאנה, te'enah,
a fig. כגרוגרת להוצאת שבת kigrogeres lehotza'as Shabbos because for carrying on
שבת Shabbos what's the minimum size that you transgress carrying? So for
all foodstuffs it is the size of a גרוגרת, grogeres, of a
dried fig.
רמון, rimon, a pomegranate.
דתנן כל כלי בעלי בתים שיעורן כרמונים. detnan kol klei ba'alei batim
shi'uran kerimonim. All the vessels of homeowners, the size is a רמון.
rimon. What does that mean? How big of a hole do I
have to have in my vessel for it no longer to be
considered a vessel for purposes of it becoming טמא? When does it
stop being a vessel? So if it is a if I'm a
storekeeper, if I'm a merchant, I'm selling the vessels, even one tiny
hole, I can't sell it anymore. Goes in the remainder stack or
something. So it stops being a vessel. Okay. If however, I'm a
homeowner, and my thing breaks a little bit, well if it gets
a little bit of a hole, fine, I'll stop using it for
keeping liquids, I'll keep olives in it. Okay, but now it's got
a hole the size of an olive. Fine, I'll keep apples and
oranges in it. At what size is the hole so big that
I throw it out? Only when it gets to be the size
of a pomegranate. Then I can't even keep pomegranates in it, what
am I going to use it for? So then I throw it
out. So pomegranate is the size of the hole that even for
a homeowner, the vessel stops being a vessel. ארץ זית שמן ודבש,
eretz zayis shemen udevash, a land of olive oil and honey. So
let's first start with זית שמן, zayis shemen, olives. ארץ שכל שיעוריה
כזיתים. eretz shekol shi'ureiha kezaysim. All of its minimum sizes are measured
by a כזית. So the גמרא Gemara says, כל שיעוריה? kol shi'ureiha?
All of the sizes? סלקא דעתך? salka dachatach? Do you really think
that's true? האיכא הני דאמרן? ha'ika hani de'amran? How about everything we
said before? There's some that are measured by a barley, and some
that are measured by, you know, by a fig. אלא אימא שרוב
שיעוריה כזיתים. ela eima sherov shi'ureiha kezaysim. Most measurements are כזית. So
if anybody asks you: what is the standard Rabbinic measurement? You would
say a כזית, right? So everything, all the forbidden foodstuffs, all the
מצוות mitzvos to eat foodstuffs, all of the amounts of, like, when
you measure amounts of things that cause טומאה, how much of a
נבלה, neveilah, how much of a מת? meis? All... almost, you know,
the standard measurement is a כזית. So that's זית. zayis. All right.
דבש, devash, honey. Now honey here is understood to be honey of
things that grow from the ground, so primarily also date honey. ככותבת
הגסה ביום הכפורים, kekoseves hagassah beyom hakippurim, like we just learned מסכת
יומא, Masechet Yoma, like a fat, you know, dried date for יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's the amount for יום כיפור Yom Kippur that
if you eat you're no longer fasting. Anyway, you have all seven
things teach you שיעורים. shi'urim. So you see אלמא דאורייתא נינהו, alma
d'oraisa ninhu, you see it's not a tradition, you see it's all
derived from the verse. So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברה? vesisbara? Does
that really make sense?
שיעורים מכתיבי? shi'urim michtivi? It doesn't... what do you mean? The verse
just gives you different foodstuffs. How do you know to match up
which foodstuff to which type of measurement it's going? Since there's absolutely
no basis in the verse to do this nice little correspondence that
you just did. אלא, ella, you have to say הלכתא נינהו וקרא
אסמכתא בעלמא. hilchesa ninhu v'kra asmakhta b'alma. You have to say that
it's just a tradition and yes it was very nice that we
quoted the verse, but that was just an אסמכתא. asmakhta. We don't
really derive it from the verse. It really is הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. Now it is very interesting to look at the
גירסא girsa here on the side and the right hand margin where
it says, you see it says ברכות מ"א ע"ב, Berachos mem aleph
amud beis, the far right in margin, מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. mi-derabbanan
v'kra asmakhta b'alma. Rather it's all rabbinic and the verse is only
an אסמכתא. asmakhta. And this raises a fascinating question about can הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai sometimes be called a דרבנן? derabbanan? Is
it sort of loosely called a דרבנן? derabbanan? Or maybe say something
opposite? הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai maybe doesn't always mean that
it's directly passed down הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai in that
sense. Maybe it means somewhat like the rabbis had latitude to define
what it meant. Right? That's an idea we had earlier on as
well. You know, that they had, you know, we had in יומא
Yoma this idea that the Torah gave the rabbis some latitude to
define what would constitute the other forms of fasting in addition to
eating and drinking. You know, so how much here is it that
the, that this is, means that it's actual the number is passed
down? Or does it actually mean that there was like latitude for
the rabbis? Ultimately it affects Torah law. When do you transgress? When
do you do the מצוה? mitzvah? This has profound implications for Torah
law, but maybe there was a certain amount of license given to
the rabbis to define it. So this issue of דרבנן derabbanan and
הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, we'll see that in a minute
as well. There is some ambiguity around the, around that. Okay, so
now we continue. So that
שיעורין Shiurin are הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. Now we still
have left חציצין chatzitzin and מחיצה. mechitza. Those are the other two.
So let's take a look.
So חציצין, chatzitzin, now, obstructions for going to the מקווה, mikvah, and
for vessels but also for people. And I want to remind everybody
that that, we're not talking specifically about נדה. niddah. In the time
of the גמרא, Gemara, we were just as easily talking about men,
right? Not just because men, because, well, once, if you have, if
you're in the time certainly when you have the תקנה takkana that
you can't, that a man couldn't דאוון daven or say ברכות brachos
if he was a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, had seminal emission, then
men are going to the מקווה mikvah at least as much as
women are, you know? So let's take a look. So it says,
so anyway, so just keep that in mind when we're talking about
חציצה. chatzitza. So חציצין דאורייתא נינהו, chatzitzin d'Oraisa ninhu, that's biblical, that
there's a, that there's an issue with חציצה. chatzitza. דכתיב, d'kesiv, the
verse says, ורחץ את בשרו במים, ve-rachatz es besaro ba-mayim, or את
כל בשרו, es kol besaro, or what's the side גירסא? girsa? You
have את בשרו? es besaro? Okay, ורחץ את בשרו במים, ve-rachatz es
besaro ba-mayim, maybe we quote the only 'besaro' later. Hold on. Okay,
anyway, ורחץ את בשרו במים, ve-rachatz es besaro ba-mayim, you wash your
flesh in water. שלא יהא דבר חוצץ בינו לבין המים, she-lo yehei
davar chotzetz beino l'vein ha-mayim, nothing should interfere, so בשרו במים, besaro
ba-mayim, nothing should be a, an obstruction between the flesh and the
water.
So you see it's learned from the פסוק, pasuk, בשרו במים. besaro
ba-mayim. What do you mean הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai? No.
So it says, no, כי אתא הלכתא, ki asa hilchesa, the הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai is coming for what purpose?
לשערו, le-sa'aro, for the purpose of telling you that the, of the
issues relating to the hair. What does this mean? כדרבה בר בר
חנה, ki-d'Rabba bar bar Chana, like Rabba bar bar Chana teaches, דאמר
רבה בר בר חנה, d'amar Rabba bar bar Chana, נימא אחת קשורה
חוצצת, nima achas kshura chotzetzas, if you have one strand of hair
which is tied onto itself like a knot in one strand of
hair, that's a חציצה chatzitza because it's a tight knot, it's one
strand tied on itself and the water can't get into the knot.
So the hair is being, you know, the hair that's part of
the knot is being blocked from water, from the water. שלוש
אינן חוצצות, shalosh einan chotzetzos, if it's three hairs that are knotted
onto themselves, so it's looser because it's, you know, it's three separate
strands that you, when you knot 'em together you're just not gonna
get as tight of a knot, so that's not a חציצה, chatzitza,
the water can get into. שתיים איני יודע, shtayim eini yodeya, two
I don't know. Now the presumably the whole purpose of quoting this
was not to get into a discussion of how many strands of
hair is a knot a חציצה chatzitza or to say that the
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai was specifically telling you X number
of strands of hair. The purpose of quoting this was only to
show you that חציצות chatzitzos matter with the hair, not only with
the flesh. Now why would you need a הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha
l'Moshe mi-Sinai? Because where do we learn חציצה chatzitza from? From the
verse that says את בשרו במים. es besaro ba-mayim. בשרו besaro has
to be במים. ba-mayim. So your flesh, not your hair. So maybe
if I only had the verse, I would have said maybe your
hair doesn't even have to go underwater, or even if it has
to go underwater, maybe a חציצה chatzitza isn't a problem because the
Torah only says בשרו במים. besaro ba-mayim. How do I know to
include the hair? That's what the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai
comes to teach you. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, שערו
נמי דאורייתא נינהו, sa'aro nami d'Oraisa ninhu, your hair is also biblical
that it has... have to touch water and go underwater. דכתיב, de-ketiv,
the verse says, ורחץ את בשרו במים, ve-rachatz et besaro bamayim, you
shall bathe your flesh with water, bathe here means immerse. And so
the דרשה drasha is, why does it say את בשרו? et besaro?
Why not just say ורחץ בשרו? ve-rachatz besaro? So את et teaches
you, את הטפל לבשרו. et ha-tafel li-besaro. את et comes to tell
you something that's an attendant to, connected to, but not the thing
itself. So את בשרו et besaro means not only your flesh, but
the את בשרו, et besaro, the thing connected to your flesh, your
hair as well. ומאי ניהו, u-mai nihu, what is that? שערו, sa'aro,
it's your hair. Right? So you know, like people know the famous
דרשה, drasha, right? ואהבת את ה' אלקיך. ve-ahavta et Hashem Elokecha. What
does את et include? Right? And that you know, so, and then
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva came and said את לרבות תלמידי חכמים. et
li-rabos talmidei chachamim. Right? Or we say ואהבת את אביך ואת אמך.
ve-ahavta et avicha ve-es imecha. את לרבות אחיך הגדול. et li-rabos achicha
ha-gadol. You know, we're always using like את, et, right? This is
נחום איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu would be דורש doreish all the
אתין etin in the תורה to tell you את et means something
connected to, associated with. So we learn it out from the word
את בשרו. et besaro. So therefore you don't need a הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai to tell you the hair. So the גמרא
Gemara says, oh,
so okay, let's try again. כי אתי הלכתא, ki-ati hilchesa, for what
purpose do we have the הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai? לכדרבי
יצחק. li-chide-Rabbi Yitzchak. Like רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק, de-amar
Rabbi Yitzchak, because רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak teaches, דאורייתא, de-Oraita, biblically, רובו
ומקפיד עליו חוצץ. rubo u-makpid alav chotzetz. What creates a חציצה chatzitzah
biblically? So biblically you need it to be most of your body,
and you have to be מקפיד, makpid, you have to not want
it on your body. Okay, so that's going to require a pretty
high threshold, pretty hard to imagine what types of things would be
a חציצה. chatzitzah. So I guess if you got like mud over
the majority of your body and you haven't gotten around to getting
it off yet. Okay, but ושאינו מקפיד עליו, ve-she-eino makpid alav, רובו
ומקפיד עליו חוצץ ושאינו מקפיד עליו אינו חוצץ. rubo u-makpid alav chotzetz
ve-she-eino makpid alav eino chotzetz. And even if it was on the
majority of your body, if you didn't care, what would be something
on the majority of your body you didn't care? Let's say for
example you had a full body cast, although that raises questions, is
that considered מקפיד makpid because you won't want it on later, but
you do want it on now. Okay, but let's say for example
you were a painter and you got paint on your body and
you didn't bother cleaning it off, that was a natural thing, although
I can't imagine on the majority of your body. Anyway, you would
need both criteria for it to be a חציצה. chatzitzah. Okay, וגזרו,
ve-gazru, then the Rabbis came along and they made a גזירה gezeirah
on רובו שאינו מקפיד משום רובו המקפיד, rubo she-eino makpid mishum rubo
ha-makpid, that if it's on the majority of your body, even if
you don't care about it, it's still a problem because if we
allow that, it'll lead to a case of majority and מקפיד, makpid,
right? So it's similar enough, it's similar that it has רוב rov
even though it doesn't have מקפיד. makpid. Okay, and similarly, and this
next category is the one that's the real issue for חציצות chatzitzas
nowadays, ועל מיעוטו המקפיד משום רובו המקפיד. ve-al mi'uto ha-makpid mishum rubo
ha-makpid. Even if it's only on the minority of your body, as
long as you're מקפיד, makpid, that rabbinically is a problem because it
has one of the two characteristics, it's מקפיד. makpid. And therefore one
of the two, that's close enough and therefore we say it's... that's
obviously the vast majority of חציצות chatzitzas nowadays are on the minority
of your body, but and the whole question boils down to how
do you define מקפיד. makpid. I think I mentioned this once before,
I'll just say it for a second. I think to some degree
it's rooted in the question of conceptually the idea of חציצה. chatzitzah.
Is the idea of חציצה chatzitzah when it's not a problem? I
mean if something's on your body and you're not מקפיד, makpid, what
difference should it make? Technically the water still isn't touching your body.
So there's two explanations. One explanation is if I'm not מקפיד, makpid,
it's like I want to leave it there and like it is
integrated and becomes part of my body. The other explanation is no,
as long as I'm not מקפיד, makpid, it's not the הלכה halacha
that the water has to touch every inch of my body. The
הלכה Halacha... is I have to fully immerse in the water and
there can't be an obstruction. So if I'm not מקפיד, makpid, it's
not designated as an obstruction. Something that I actively don't want there
is seen as a foreign body and an obstruction. Something that I
don't care one way or the other, okay, the water didn't touch
me, but there's not a הלכה Halacha the water has to touch,
it's just I have to be fully immersed and there's no obstruction.
That doesn't qualify as an obstruction. There's a big difference between the
two because if you say that I have to make it part
of my body, you demand a much higher threshold. It's not enough
just that I don't care that it's there. In some way I
have to actively want it there for it to be integrated and
considered part of my body. If you say the whole issue is
that
as long as you're not trying to actively get rid of it,
it's not considered an obstruction, that means most cases I don't care
one way or the other, I haven't even thought about it, big
deal, right? So there's a huge question about חציצות, chatzitzas, what defines
אינו מקפיד. eino makpid. The all the halachic questions about חציצה, chatzitzah,
not all, but the vast majority are that question. If you have
a very high threshold because conceptually you need to make it almost
part of the body, you actively want it on and you need
it on, and maybe like it's you need it on like stitches
that can't come out and other types of things, or is it
an issue that just I don't care one way or the other
and then it's much easier to say it's not a problem. Okay,
so that is the idea of מקפיד. makpid. Biblically you need both,
the majority and and מקפיד, Makbid, rabbinically one or the other is
enough to be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says בליגזור נמי
על מידי שאינו מקפיד משום מידי המקפיד. Beligzar nami al midei she'eino
makbid mishum midei hamakbid. Let's make a... let's... as long as we're
at it, let's say even a minority that's אינו מקפיד, Eino Makbid,
you know, that'll lead to a case that's also somewhat at least...
I mean, it's some... there, it's something in the same פרשה. Parsha.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. אי נמי משום רובו שאינו מקפיד
Ei nami mishum rubo she'eino makbid or let's say even a majority...
I'm sorry, did I say... נמי על מידי שאינו מקפיד משום מידי
המקפיד Nami al midei she'eino makbid mishum midei hamakbid because if you
allow a מידי שאינו מקפיד Midei she'eino makbid it'll lead to a
מידי המקפיד, Midei hamakbid, אי נמי משום רובו שאינו מקפיד Ei nami
mishum rubo she'eino makbid or lead to a majority that you're not
מקפיד. Makbid. היא גופא. Hi gufa. The גמרא Gemara answers no. היא
גופא גזירה ואנן ניקום וניגזור גזירה לגזירה? Hi gufa gzeira ve'anan neikum
venigzar gzeira ligzeira? That itself is a גזירה. Gzeira. What, are we
going to come and make a גזירה Gzeira to a גזירה? Gzeira?
This is the classic principle that you don't make
a גזירה לגזירה. Gzeira ligzeira. Straight to you visual... this is hopefully
will help you in general to give you the idea of גזירה
לגזירה. Gzeira ligzeira. I don't know if it will or not. But
if you think about this as, right, as a...
you have a 2x2. Just use four. Okay. So you have
here, okay... so you have
רובו Rubo and מיעוטו Mi'uto
and מיעוטו Mi'uto whatever and מקפיד Makbid
and אינו מקפיד, Eino Makbid, right? You have like all four possibilities,
right? So רוב ומקפיד, Rov umakbid, this is the דאורייתא De'oraita problem.
Right?
Okay. Now, anything that's similar to it in one direction is אסור,
Assur, is a דרבנן. Derabbanan. מיעוט המקפיד, Mi'ut hamakbid, it shares... they're
similar because they're... המקפיד Hamakbid row. So that's a דרבנן Derabbanan problem.
רוב ואינו מקפיד Rov ve'eino makbid is similar on the רוב Rov
column. So that's דרבנן. Derabbanan. This is not similar either on the
רוב Rov or on the column. It has, right, it's dissimilar in
two ways. So this is actually מותר, Mutar, מיעוט שאינו מקפיד. Mi'ut
she'eino makbid. Okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara says, right? So the
גמרא Gemara said, well why not say this should be אסור Assur
because if we let this it'll lead to that? So if we
allow this, right, it'll lead to a מיעוט המקפיד Mi'ut hamakbid or
if we allow a מיעוט שאינו מקפיד Mi'ut she'eino makbid it'll lead
to a רוב ואינו מקפיד. Rov ve'eino makbid. And the answer is
no, because that's still two degrees away
from getting back to the core of the problem. It's a גזירה
לגזירה, Gzeira ligzeira, right? This is a גזירה Gzeira and this is
a גזירה. Gzeira. This is מותר Mutar because to make this אסור
Assur because it'll lead to this, but this is a גזירה. Gzeira.
It has to go two degrees to get back to the דאורייתא
De'oraita problem. Okay, so that's the principle that we don't make a
גזירה לגזירה. Gzeira ligzeira. Now, here's the question. So that's all very
nice. That's הלכות חציצה. Hilchot Chatzitza. Where's the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
Lemoshe Misinai in any of this?
Right? We said, oh, the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai is
to tell us all this stuff about רוב המקפיד Rov hamakbid and
מיעוט המקפיד. Mi'ut hamakbid. What's the הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha Lemoshe Misinai?
What did we say הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha Lemoshe Misinai? We said
דבר תורה Devar Torah רוב ומקפיד Rov umakbid and דרבנן Derabbanan one
of the
two.
Which
isn't...
but if the דרבנן Derabbanan isn't הלכה... halacha so the דרבנן...
Derabbanan... so what's the only possible thing here that's the הלכה למשה
מסיני? Halacha Lemoshe Misinai? The words דבר תורה. Devar Torah. So look
at רש"י, Rashi, דבר תורה הלכה למשה מסיני. Devar Torah Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai. Okay. So רש"י Rashi says דבר תורה Devar Torah normally we
say means דאורייתא, De'oraita, but it is true that we didn't have
any פסוק Pasuk to start... Where do we get started off to
say רוב ומקפיד, Rov umakbid, right? So there was no פסוק Pasuk
that started it off with that idea. So רש"י Rashi says, oh
no, that initial definition, quantification of חציצה Chatzitza is the הלכה למשה
מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. To quantify חציצה Chatzitza as רוב ומקפיד. Rov
umakbid. And then the rabbis come and they make the other גזירות.
Gzeirot. But that's the standard explanation. But you might remember I told
you a second ago that the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot calls
the שיעורין... shiurin, what did it say by the שיעורין? The גמרא
Gemara in ברכות? Berachot? It calls it דרבנן, Derabbanan, right? That there's
some ambiguity of הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai and דרבנן. Derabbanan.
So there are some ראשונים Rishonim that actually say, the מאירי Meiri
has this, that when it says דרבנן Derabbanan we don't allow, you
know, we don't allow either רוב אינו מקפיד Rov eino makbid or
מיעוט המקפיד, Mi'ut hamakbid, says that's the הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai. The גזירת דרבנן, Gzeirat Derabbanan, which is like crazy, because when
do we ever hear of גזירה Gzeira and הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha
Lemoshe Misinai? הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai is classically like a
technical thing that's passed down. A גזירה Gzeira is a classic rabbinic
legislation. But I mentioned this because this passage is not clear in
this thing, which one are we identifying as the הלכה למשה מסיני?
Halacha Lemoshe Misinai? רש"י Rashi identifies this, our core part. But the
מאירי Meiri quotes those that say no, the rabbinic גזירה Gzeira is
what's being labeled הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, which then challenges
our idea of what הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai means if
you can call a rabbinic גזירה Gzeira הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai. So that's not the standard explanation, but I just did want
to share that with you. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara is
the third... so we have
שיעורין and... So מחיצין הא דאמרי. Mechitzin ha d'amrei.
So מחיצה, Mechitza,
we said, where's מחיצה Mechitza הלכה למשה מסיני? Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai? We
need to know the idea of 10 טפחים. tefachim. So that, that
size of a מחיצה, mechitza, I don't know why it's not wrapped
up in שיעורין, but the minimum size of a מחיצה, mechitza, that's
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai. So the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא
לרבי יהודה. hani-cha le-Rabbi Yehuda.
That's good according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that didn't learn it
out from the ארון aron or from the כרובים. keruvim. You need
to know the idea of a size of מחיצה mechitza is 10
טפחים tefachim from there. אלא לרבי מאיר מאי איכא למימר?
Ella le-Rabbi Meir mai
ika le-meimar? According to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that learns it from
the ארון aron and the כרובים, keruvim, right? Because we sort of
linked where you could learn it from the ארון aron and כרובים
keruvim to another debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir about measurements. So according to him that you could link
it to there, so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? Where is
מחיצה mechitza הלכה למשה מסיני? Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai? 10 טפחים tefachim we
already know from the ארון aron and the כרובים. keruvim. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, כי אתא הלכתא ki ata hilkhata there's a
lot of other הלכות halakhot. about מחיצה mechitza that you need הלכה
למשה מסיני. Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai. לגוד Legud and לבוד lavud and דופן
עקומה. dofen akuma. For all the things we're going to be dealing
with a lot when we do סוכה, Sukkah, which is what I've
been calling the magic extending wall and the magic bending wall and
all those things are also הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai. So
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, 10 טפחים. tefachim. According to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he knows 10 טפחים tefachim elsewhere, but the idea
that if you start with a מחיצה, mechitza, you can imagine it
to go, you know, all the way up or you can imagine
it to go all the way down, or if you have a
מחיצה mechitza connected to פסול סכך, pasul skhakh, you can imagine the
מחיצה mechitza to bend, right, or that if it's within three טפחים
tefachim of the סכך, skhakh, it's like it's connected. All of those
magic, you know, types of things of a מחיצה, mechitza, that obviously
is not based on any פסוק, pasuk, that all is tradition, that
all is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai. I do again want
to reiterate the interesting question about where we're doing the measurements and
what the measurement is set in reference to. Are we doing an
internal measurement of 10 טפחים, tefachim, you know, from the floor to
the bottom of the סכך skhakh or an external measurement? There is
one question. A related question is, what's invalid when it's less than
10 טפחים? tefachim? Is the סכך skhakh invalid or the wall invalid?
And that could have relevance for certain הלכות. So if we learn
from one פסוק pasuk where the כרובים סוככים, keruvim sokhekhim, shaded and
made a canopy, and it has to be 10 טפחים tefachim to
define it as a canopy, that means it's a problem in the
סכך, skhakh, not a problem in the wall, it's a problem in
the סכך. skhakh. But the גמרא Gemara here seems to say whether
a מחיצה mechitza has to be 10 טפחים tefachim is based on
this question of the size of a סוכה. Sukkah. So that seems
to say that it's a question of defining the wall. So it's
an interesting issue here about, you know, both what is the source
of 10 טפחים tefachim for a סוכה, Sukkah, how much is it
about this all stuff in the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, which again
is very powerful in terms of the imagery of a סוכה, Sukkah,
or how much is it just an arbitrary number? And then a
related question of, are we defining the height of the wall or
are we defining the height of the סכך, skhakh, where is the
problem considered to be located? And some of that has to do
with the various sources as we've been discussing. This one emphasized מחיצה
mechitza is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha LeMoshe MiSinai. The פסוק pasuk about
the כרובים keruvim and the סוככים sokhekhim and a canopy emphasizes the
concern is with the סכך. skhakh. Okay, now we continue. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabbanan, so our rabbis taught.
שתים כהלכתן, Shtayim ke-hilkhatan, two as the walls are normal, והשלישית אפילו
טפח. ve-hashlishit afilu tefach. And the third wall can be even a
טפח. tefach. Okay, and we're going to have a whole discussion tomorrow
where that טפח tefach is situated. But what we're going to start
with today is where do we know basically the numbers? Hold on,
I just have to see if it's not an emergency. Okay, fine.
So, and the third one is even a טפח. tefach. במאי קמיפלגי?
be-mai kama miflegi? What's the debate about? I'm sorry, I skipped a
line. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, Rabbi Shimon says, שלוש כהלכתן
ורביעית אפילו טפח. shalosh ke-hilkhatan ve-revi'it afilu tefach. No, he demands an
extra wall. Three have to be normal, the fourth one can be
even a טפח. tefach. So במאי קמיפלגי? be-mai kama miflegi? What's the
debate? רבנן סברי יש אם למסורת. Rabbanan savri yesh em la-mesoret. The
Rabbis say there is a mother to the מסורת, mesoret, which means
it's a way of saying that if the verse is written one
way and read another way, which one
serves as the primary basis for halakhic derivation? The way it's written
or the way it's read? So מסורת, mesoret, tradition, means the way
it's read because, you know, the way it's written is in tradition,
it's just the stuff that's written that everybody has access to. The
tradition is something external to the text. So יש אם למסורת yesh
em la-mesoret means we focus by the tradition of how it's read.
As opposed to יש אם למקרא. yesh em la-mikra. No, you know
what, I got that wrong. I'm always getting it confused because logically
it doesn't work that way. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says מסורת mesoret
actually means, I'm sorry, reverse that. מסורת mesoret means the way it
actually is written. Yeah, I never understand why that's the way. מסורת
mesoret means the way the text has been handed down, the way
it's written. מקרא Mikra means the way it is actually read. So
okay, so יש אם למסורת yesh em la-mesoret means that it is
based, you base your halakhic derivation on the way it's
written. רבי שמעון סבר... Rabbi Shimon savar... and Rebbi Shimon says you
base your halachic definition, a derivation, on the way that it is
that it is read. Okay, interesting use of the word אם, eim,
right? Mother, like where do we see that before? I mean you
know we sort of say like, you know we have the expression
in English, right, necessity is the mother of invention, right? Something gives
birth to the following ideas. But normally when you talk about what,
you know, where you apply your hermeneutic derivations, it just is a
fascinating phrase, both because as you see I myself got confused with
מסורת mesores and what refers to what, but also the use of
the word אם. eim. Anyway, so how does this work? רבנן סברי
יש אם למסורת. Rabbanan savri yeish eim lamesores. The Rabbis say you
focus on the way that it is written. Now what verse are
we even talking about? So בסכת בסכת בסוכות. basukot, basukot, basukot. It
says three times in the Torah you shall dwell in סוכות. sukkot.
Twice it says it without a ו, vav. see that's בסכת בסכת.
basukat, basukat. We read it בסוכות, basukot, but it's written without a
ו. vav. And once it's written with a ו. vav. So if
you start by the way it's written, basically the idea's going to
be the following. Every time it has the word סוכה, sukkah, it
tells you other than the first time. The first is needed to
tell you live in a סוכה. sukkah. After there it's seen as
superfluous. You don't have to repeat the word סוכה sukkah again, right?
It's just the antecedent, so you could just, you know, you could
say בו, bo, sit in it or whatever. Why do you keep
on repeating the word סוכה? sukkah? So every extra time it says
the word סוכה sukkah after the first is seen as telling you
the need for x number of walls. All you count up the
number of סוכות sukkot it says and that's the number of walls
that you need. That somehow is the assumption. So it says twice
בסכת basukat without a ו. vav So if we're going יש אם
למסורת, yeish eim lamesores, the way it's written, then that counts as
singular even though it's read in the plural. So that's two. And
בסוכות basukot is in the plural, that's two more, that's four. הרי
כאן ארבע, harei kan arba, that gives you four units to use.
חד לגופיה, chad leguphah, you need one unit for the basic point
of the פסוק pasuk itself, live in a סוכה. sukkah. פשלו להו
תלתא, pashlu leu tlatasa, you're given, you're left with three, three units
equals three walls. שמעתא כהלכתא, shmata kehilkhasa, so two go the normal
way, הלכה למשה מסיני, halachah lemoshe misinai, and then there's a הלכה
למשה מסיני halachah lemoshe misinai that comes along that we forgot to
mention, דגרעה לשלישית, degarsa leshlishis, and tells you the third one doesn't
have to be a third one, it takes away from the third
one, ואוקמתה בטפח, v'ukmata betefach, a representative third wall is enough, just
a טפח. tefach. So basically you start with four units based on
the way it's written, not the way it's read, and that gets
you to, you discount the first one, it gets you to three
walls. רבי שמעון סבר יש אם למקרא. Rebbi Shimon savar yeish eim
lemikra. Rebbi Shimon says no, you don't go by the way it's
written, you go by the way it's read. בסוכות בסוכות בסוכות. basukot,
basukot, basukot. It's read in the plural each time. So that gives
six units, each one counts for two. הרי כאן ששה, harei kan
shisha, that's six. חד קרא לגופיה, chad kra leguphah, now you need
one of the בסוכות, basukot, which is two, you need one of
those words to tell you the simple sense of the פסוק, pasuk,
live in a סוכה. sukkah. So you're really left with two times
it says בסוכות, basukot, which is four. פשלו ארבע, pashlu arba, you're
left with four. שלשה כהלכתן, shlosha kehilkhata, so three normal, ואתא הלכתא
וגרעה לרביעית ואוקמתה בטפח, v'atha hilkheta v'garsah lerivita v'ukmata betefach, and הלכה
למשה מסיני halachah lemoshe misinai tells you the fourth one is enough
to be representative, just a טפח. tefach. Okay, so basically the way
it works is how many times does the Torah say how many
סוכות sukkas does the Torah refer to, and it refers to, you
know, according to after the first use of the word סוכה, sukkah,
so according to one you have
three units, according to the other you have four units, and that
gets you the debate of three walls versus four walls. Okay, that's
one explanation. איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, if you want I'll say, דכולי
עלמא יש אם למקרא. d'kulei alma yeish eim lemikra. Everybody says you
go by the way it's read, which should have given you then
you use so if it's the way it's read it's six, you
discount the first one, which is a double, so you're left with
four, so that should have given you four walls. So what's the
debate? הכא בהא קמיפלגי. hakha behakha mifligi. Here's the debate. מר סבר
סכך בעי קרא. mar savar skhakh ba'ei kra.
No, one of the words, one of the units have to tell
you just dwell in a סוכה. sukkah. Then you have four units.
But of those four units, maybe you need one unit to tell
you that you need סכך skhakh in your סוכה. sukkah. How why
you start using the units to teach you the number of walls?
Use the units to teach you first of all that you need
סכך. skhakh. ומר סבר, umar savar, the other one says, סכך לא
בעי קרא. skhakh lo ba'ei kra. You don't need a verse for
the סכך. skhakh. Okay, so right, people get what we're doing here,
right? Right,
it says בסוכות, basukot, right, תשבו, teshvu, whatever, כי בסוכות הושבתי, ki
basukot hoshavti, and
I whatever, it says בסוכות basukot whatever, so x number of times.
So if you go by the way that it's written, you have
a I don't even know if the ו vav, is a מלא
malei the first one or not. Anyway, this is written in the
singular, it's just without the ו, that's written in the plural, two,
one, one, gives you four units to use. You need one unit
to tell you live in a סוכה. sukkah. Live in a סוכה.
sukkah. And then you have three remaining to tell you three walls.
Of course the first unit is in the plural so you really
only
well, I don't is that true? I just made it up. I
don't know. Is it? Is it? Okay, anyway, but we get to
decide now how to assign the units. That's one approach. The other
approach says no, it's read in the plural, so that's six, okay,
but one of the words tells you live in a סוכה, Sukkah,
so you have to use two units to do that, and use
four units to tell you four walls. That's the first thing that
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but then it says one minute, if
we've got six units and now we've got down, you need two
to tell you live in a סוכה, Sukkah, we've got it down
to four. Why do you jump to say four walls? The four
should tell you all the components of a סוכה. Sukkah. It should
first have to tell you one unit tells you you need סכך,
Sechach,
that's
for one unit, and the other three tell you you need three
walls, right? So we're learning the different components. Let's learn it that
way, and that'll get you three walls, not four walls. So the
other says no, no, no, you don't need a פסוק Pasuk for
סכך. Sechach. You don't need a unit for סכך. Sechach. Why not?
Because the word סוכה Sukkah itself, the whole idea of סוכה Sukkah
is סכך, Sechach, and therefore, as soon as you say dwell in
a סוכה, Sukkah, you're saying dwell under סכך. Sechach. So it's already
sort of included in like the basic meaning of the פסוק. Pasuk.
Now, the reason this is conceptually important, as I told you before,
like the first רש״י Rashi of the מסכת Masechet says על שם
הסכך קרויה סוכה, al shem hasechach keruyah sukkah, right? How much do
you sort of see the סכך Sechach as the basic definition and
the walls are some secondary requirement, or how much do you see
the סכך Sechach and the walls of like equally important? So in
a way, that's what the גמרא Gemara is discussing here, whether, you
know, again, it's like this technical issue of numbers, right? So it
seems very like mechanical, but there is a conceptual issue that the
גמרא Gemara is raising, which is how much is the סכך Sechach
essentially the identity of a סוכה Sukkah and you don't even need
to discuss it, or how much is it, no, it's a component
the same way the walls are a component and they're all sort
of at an equal level. Okay, so that's approach number
two: מר סבר סוכה בקרא ומר סבר סוכה לא בקרא. mar savar
sukkah bikra umar savar sukkah lo bikra. ואיבעית אימא, V’iba’is eima, if
you want I’ll tell you, דכולי עלמא יש אם למסורת, de’chulei alma
yesh em l’masores, you go by the way that it is
written, והכא בהא קמיפלגי, v’hacha b’ha kamiflegi, so that would start you
with four. Here's the debate. And then you use one for the
basic purpose of the verse itself, but you're left with three. So
if you're left with three, what's the debate? Here's the
debate. מר סבר כי אתא הלכתא לגרוע, mar savar ki ata hilchesa
ligroa, that the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai is coming and
tell you that three, it's coming to say yeah, but not a
full three, the third one can be representative, could be a טפח.
tefach. ומר סבר, U’mar savar, the other one holds, כי אתא הלכתא
להוסיף. ki ata hilchesa lehosif. No, actually, it's telling you fundamentally three,
but three plus. So therefore, we all agree we start with three,
but then there's a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. Does the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai say three plus a little bit,
or does it say three but only a representative third? So is
the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai decreasing or adding? That's another way
of understanding it. ואיבעית אימא, V’iba’is eima, if you want I’ll tell
you, דכולי עלמא כי אתא הלכתא לגרוע, de’chulei alma ki ata hilchesa
ligroa, everybody agrees that the הלכה is coming to take
away, so you would should be if you start with three, you
take away one, you're left with two and a bit. So what's
the debate? ויש אם למסורת, v’yesh em l’masores, and you go by
the way it is written. So if you go by the way
it's written, so you need one for the core use of the
verse and then you're left with three, then you should go down
to two and a half. So what's the debate? Here, והכא בדורשין
תחילות קמיפלגי. v’hacha b’dorishin techilos kamiflegi. The debate is, can you explicate,
can you use for this type of math and for this type
of derivations, the first reference in the verse? We've been saying all
along, the first reference is off limits. The first reference is needed
for פשט. pshat. You can only start counting the additional references. So
maybe not, maybe I'm entitled to count even the first reference, and
then I would start with four rather than starting with three. Okay.
מר סבר, Mar savar, one holds, דורשין תחילות, dorishin techilos, you can
start with the first one, you can use the first reference, so
you start with four, so four gets you down to three and
a
half. ומר סבר, U’mar savar, and the other one says no, you
don't start with the first one, you start with three and you
get down to two and a half. So all that was very
interesting, it was a lot of math or a lot of just,
yeah, how many numbers do you count? It wasn't really conceptual at
all except for the question in the middle, one possibility of whether
סכך Sechach is the intrinsic identity of the סוכה. Sukkah. But of
course, if I told you there was a debate of two and
a half walls or three and a half walls, you would probably
immediately assume that they're debating how permanent-like, how house-like does the סוכה
Sukkah have to be? That means two and a half is not
much of a serious structure. That's a real representation of דירת עראי,
diras arai, of a סוכה Sukkah as temporary. Three and a bit
already is much more protective and is much more house-like, and maybe
that's more like סוכה דירת קבע. Sukkah diras keva. Well, in a
way, that's what the גמרא Gemara says right
here. Okay, רב מתנה אמר, Rav Masna amar, רב מתנה Rav Masna
says, טעמא דרבי שמעון מהכא, tama d’Rabbi Shimon meihacha, here's the reason
of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. וסוכה תהיה לצל יומם, V’sukkah tihyeh l’tzel
yomam, this is the verse we started the מסכת Masechet with from
ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, this vision of of the times of משיח, Mashiach, and
it like and that also is a vision of God's cloud and
God's divine presence hovering over, you know, ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So and so
also very important that type of
imagery. So anyway, so there's the imagery of God's presence in a
cloud with the messianic sort of tinge, and that is God's presence
is a סוכה sukkah is a covering over. And this is what
the פסוק pasuk says. So it's not talking about the halachic סוכה,
sukkah, but it is talking about this word of the סוכה sukkah
which is connected, as we saw in the beginning of the מסכת,
masechet, at least by some to the halachic סוכה. sukkah. And it
shall be a canopy or a covering, לצל יומם, l'tzel yomam, for
shade in the day, מחורב mechorev from the heat, ולמחסה ולמסתור מזרם
וממטר, ul'machseh u'lmistor mizerem u'mimatat,
and for a protection and a shielding from the sort
of from the storm and the rain and the rain. Okay, which
means that a סוכה sukkah is not enough just to give shade.
A סוכה sukkah actually has to protect you from the elements. So
part of what's protecting you from the elements is not just the
סכך, schach, but the walls. Okay? So therefore, if the walls are
part of the protection and it's not just shade, but protection, then
walls are also have need to be more and you need three
and a bit and not two and a bit. Which by the
way is interesting, it's not saying it's just דירת ארעי dirat arai
versus דירת קבע, dirat keva, which to me would have been the
easiest boxes to put it in. It's actually also we a minute
ago were talking about are the סכך schach and the walls of
a different level of importance? Well in a way, what the גמרא
Gemara here is having רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say is, the walls
are an equal part of what the protection of a סוכה sukkah
is about. So they're equally important to the סכך. schach. It's not
just about shade, it's about protection from all directions, if you want
to think about the ענני כבוד ananei kavod of all directions. So
the walls
actually are equally important as the סכך schach or have to do
an equal function and it's not just about the shade. Okay, so
it's a I think it's a powerful idea because the גמרא Gemara
before also said that according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you don't
need a פסוק pasuk for the... no, forget that, that actually works.
Anyway, so it's interesting now, the idea of three and a half
walls leads us to,
conceptually rather if you get beyond the numbers, can be read as
the way I just suggested, which is I think sort of the
most obvious boxes to put it in, דירת ארעי dirat arai versus
דירת קבע. dirat keva. But also what the גמרא Gemara says is
it actually makes us think about the function of a סוכה. sukkah.
If the function is is it just shade and then it's all
about the סכך schach or is it about protection from the elements?
And then the walls are included as well and then you actually
might need more walls but it raises the importance of the walls.
Yes, Charlie. Two things.
First, we're back to the beginning of this they were talking about
spellings and there's an Amoraic statement in קידושין Kiddushin that says that
we lost the מסורה masorah for the exact spellings of the words.
But here we're deriving הלכה from spellings. Yeah, I mean, the גמרא
Gemara
just because we lost it doesn't mean we have no idea, there's
a certain amount of imprecision. But yes, it is a good point
that the גמרא Gemara often does this, plays with the exact spellings
and assumes that we do it based on what we have. But
talking about the spellings, I wanted to point out that on the
word סוכה sukkah that there's a very famous and cute גר"א Gra
who says that the word סוכה sukkah basically represents the standard configurations
of a סוכה. sukkah. Because this is basically four walls, this is
basically three walls, and this is two walls and a bit. So
there you go. So cute. I don't know what's this this.
The second second thing is this last פסוק pasuk is from נביא,
Navi, not from...
Yeah, but again, we did it at the beginning of the מסכת.
masechet. It's revealing what the meaning of the word סוכה sukkah is.
But at the beginning we did it for the exact opposite reason.
We said the shade is what's important. That's why it has to
be less than twenty אמה. ammah.
Right, it looked at the first half of the פסוק.
pasuk. And they actually say it's because the shade is more important,
it's linked in, the protection is sort of less important. Now we're
going to...
Yeah, it's a good point. It's a very good point. I see
the first I mean they were different אמוראים, Amoraim, but
you're right, he ended before the לצל יומם, l'tzel yomam, he ended
by סוכה תהיה לצל יומם, Sukkat t'hiyeh l'tzel yomam, he didn't look
at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. And here he incorporates. He
discounts it and here he incorporates. Yes, that's an excellent point. Okay,
so we will end here for today.